so often we talk about
endurance and during the unpleasantness
and feeling
and during the pleasantly reason feeling
so
how would you practically do that
or rather let's start at this
how would the non or how do failing to
endure how would that manifest
how would that manifest
failing to endure unpleasantly arisen
feeling say something something bothers you
say something something bothers you
and you fail to endure it how did you
know you failed to endure it
what is it that qualifies failure of
enduring it
and not mindfulness not recollecting
and you won't know that you're failing
because you're not even aware exactly so
what is actually there
you would know you're failing what is
that what would qualified
when you're doing something to distract
yourself so when you're doing something
yes you went acting out of it so when
you acted out of it
when you acted out of anger or acted out
of loss you can review yeah
so although the action might not have
necessarily even been
like sufficient to break the precepts
nevertheless you know for yourself
and if you look you will find out even
if you ignored it
that you acted out of it you chose to
act out of lust or other aversion or out
of
distraction so that's how you know you
fail to endure it
so then what you do in order to endure
it
interesting you don't act out of it yeah
whatever's you can't change that so and
the reason why i'm going this way it's
because yeah you might think also i must
be mindful of it no
mindfulness will come out of it by not
acting out of it
but it's really acting or not acting out
of it that's where sila comes first
it's always the same order so by not
acting out of
discomfort that somebody upset you or
something you know you're enduring it now sure
you know you're enduring it now sure
you're enduring not acting physically
now you're not acting verbally not even
saying something on account of it
you become skilled in that developed in
that you'll be able to endure
mentally as well not having certain
thoughts on account of that same
experience
and means at any point
throughout that proper enduring by not
acting out of it
you are mindful you are forcing yourself
to be mindful by not acting out of
things the only way to not act out of things is
the only way to not act out of things is
to not lose the sight of them not forget
so by prioritizing the not acting out of
these things
you are like cultivating mindfulness
you're saying so watch guarding that
gateway well exactly yeah that brings
that next point so you recognize ah
that's it's it's mind choosing to
act out of lust that's how you accept
lust not by having lusterism it's mind
not by having lusterism it's mind
choosing to act out of ill will
how you accept the will again not by a
reason on its own
so that's the gateway that's the doorway
through which these things have to
arrive and i let them in i open the door by
and i let them in i open the door by
acting out
i invite you so it's your choice and
it's your choice to open the door and
act out of it that's what i mean
like that's what like you you don't
necessarily have to worry about i must
be mindful every second of this no i
just be my
i must be mindful like peripherally i
mustn't lose the sight of
what i'm about to do i don't need to
keep okay this is what i'm feeling this
is what i'm feeling this is what i'm
feeling this is what i feel
so you need to recognize that it's your
choice for lust
to increase yeah it's your choice
basically to as i said
to to to open the door it's the simile
we gave before like somebody comes at
your doorstep and kind of
tries to pressure you to let them in but
you are the one it's your choice to open
the door or leave it closed
and sometimes people can't bear that
pressure well often
you start by not even being able to bear
that pressure so then you open the door
to chase them away
but then it was oh you open the door
that's all they want you to
they don't care if you open the door to
let them in or change them away they
want you to open the door because
they'll find a way in if you open the
door so often people think i must get rid of
so often people think i must get rid of
this so they open the door
and engage with the last oriole will and
that's why they become
involved with it so they chose to open
it so you don't want to open the door
and that's that endurance we talk about
it's there pressuring you you're not
acting out of it
and you're not trying to get rid of it
if there's the unpleasant
pressure don't try to get rid of it
if there is like pleasant pressure
towards pleasure
don't welcome it don't go towards it
so remain unengaged with it keep the
door closed
the gateway guard it guard the gateway
you don't need to be policing
what is arising for you and what
pressures you what hindrance is present
currently all you need to do is stay at a gateway
all you need to do is stay at a gateway
because that's where these things will
become a problem
and again that's why the wisdom word is
like knowing where the problem is
it's it's like it's a necessary basis
for any wisdom to arise
so the problem is not in that i heard
something that upset me
the problem is nothing that nothing that
i seen something that that made my mind
lustful the problem is that when those things do
the problem is that when those things do
arise i have no concept where the
gateway is where the problem is
and i am automatically engaged or
automatically repelled
and i'm acting out of repulsion or
repulsion or acting out of a lust
towards it
i cannot not act and the reason why you
cannot not act is because you don't know
where the gateway is
you've never tried it and you don't know
where the gateway is yeah because you
just kept acting out of it
and kept either trying to get rid of it
or dismissing it as a problem
the option of the middle way
so what i'm describing is basically
exactly that
middleweight becomes an option for you
you can still choose to act out or not
but now you see
that the choice is on you and that's
already a choice in itself
that you become aware of so by
abstaining from opening door for lust to welcome it
from opening door for lust to welcome it
or
by abstaining from opening door for a
virgin to go and get rid of it
you are choosing the middle way through
not to choosing to not act out of these
to choosing to not act out of these
things you are choosing the middle way
and you start to see it so that's why
you you guard your mind correctly and
you you go above
you go above the five hindrances
anything that bothers whether the
central nature ill will restlessness
death doubt sluggishness confusion
ah and either of those things are a prob
a problem in in themselves by arising
their problem in me being
under them affected by them involved
with them and you're always involved
through the same gateway of you
choosing to open the door and act out of
it
so bearing the five hindrances correctly
and during them correctly yeah the mind
will rise above them
not preventing them from arising
the five door knockers yeah exactly
yeah the five the five uh unwelcome
visitors
but like that's you want to understand
that as i said it's not in themselves
that they hinder you
they become hindrance and for that you
are responsible so things that
hinder you cease to be the hindrance
but they don't necessarily disappear
themselves
so how do you then practically not act
out of these things what do you do
how can you help that not acting out of
out of hindrances
out of unpleasant things
i just said not to to recognize them
and not act out of them but what if you
actually out of it
would it if you have yeah you forgot you
got careless
then just recollect yourself
basically how
can what
you can't you can't undo what you've
just done
so you have to just so what exactly do
you need to recollect
just oh i made a mistake i'll try again
i'll do better next time or what what do
you want to recollect
whatever whatever's there now so if i
if i've acted out of lust then
i recognize that that's
like i see that it i wasn't very clear
with what i was doing so how did that
lack of clarity come about then
so how can you prevent so lack of
clarity was then
the basis for you acting out so what can
you do
what can you see here and now they will
pertain to that helping that like
whatever i'm feeling
so you're feeling remorse yeah
so how can that help you not lose
clarity in regard to the future lost
non-reason lost
you're remorseful now
it can actually help you but how what is
it that you have to see in regard to the
remorse they will then help you in regard to
they will then help you in regard to
future honors and lust
that will arise
it's not the decisions and
determinations you make on account of
being remorseful for something bad
you've done
that in indirect way what is a direct
thing that if you see in regard to your
remorse on account of mistakes you made they
on account of mistakes you made they
will
there and then approach the basis of
those mistakes in the future
if you if you sustain it non-resistance
to that displeasure
and what well how do we call that
non-resistance to displeasure
of remorse in this case
the gateway so the gateway that you lost
the site of
in regard to lust or real will or
whatever you acted out of
is the same way is the same gateway
now in regard to the displeasure of
remorse and if you're still not seeing it means
and if you're still not seeing it means
none of your determinations of i'll
never do this again
will be actually rooted in anything
substantial there could be like
circumstantial determinations because it
made you feel
bad but if you actually see that oh
now i'm also ignoring the gateway
through which this remorse pressures me
by not ignoring the gateway by
clarifying the seeing of the gateway of
your responsibility in regard to it
you know that i don't need to worry
about what specific lust
or annoyance will arise in the future
all i need to worry about is not losing
the sight
of this gateway here and now
okay because and that's when you don't
need to rekindle the old last to prove
to yourself that you're beyond like no
any all of these things can only enter
through a gateway all you need to do is
see a gateway on account of eight
hindrance and you deal with all the hindrances but
and you deal with all the hindrances but
you see that
you know that you went down that
path of lust because you lost sight of
the gateway in the first place so yeah
that's what you recognize so they
recognize the gateway i recognize the
cure you you support the recognition of the
you you support the recognition of the
gateway not by making the termination
that never in the future you will lose
the sight of the gateway
but by actually practically not losing
the sight of the gateway there and then
while you're remorseful thinking about
it
present here and now to be visible here
and now
yes that's something that i'll do
tomorrow well exactly because that's
always the implication
everybody you know it has to be you you
have you kind of you start wrongly and
then you start basically being less and
less wrong so to speak so yeah
so i made the mistake because of a
problem that's always present
exactly ignoring of the gateway it's not
something going to be done in the future
or something that has been done in the
past whenever it was done it was
relevant because it was done presently
and and that's why it's a gateway
doesn't matter when
like that which didn't come through the
gate gateway last to the version doesn't
matter where it is
unless it's at the gateway so that's the
whole point the simile of the of the of
the sim of the town
like with with big walls around which is
only one way in or out
and the wise man recognizes that so he
doesn't have to go and chase
people that cause lust or people that
cause ill will
and police them all he needs to do i
just need to stay at the gateway and not
let them in and there will be no trouble
in the town
when they are not at a gateway entering
the town
i don't care where they are and what
they do and when they turn up
all i care is protecting the gateway
and that gateway is not a random chance
it's not a mistake it's not a momentary
slip of mindfulness
it's always intentional choice to open
it
hence literally the entire dhamma
boils down to one instruction that the
buddha gave often to
numerous monks and nuns whatever you
know it's wholesome
do it whenever you know it's rooted in
unwholesome don't do it not like pray that it will
don't do it not like pray that it will
come your way or something no
do it or don't do it it's a matter of
choice so if you cultivate the right choices
so if you cultivate the right choices
sufficient enough you get to understand
and uproot the nature of lust aversion
delusion and distraction
you get to fully discern the gateway and
be unable to lose the sight of it
that's why arahant is always mindful not
because he's always
i'm at the gateway i'm a gateway no it's
because he fully proficiently developed
himself in regard to he cannot not see
it anymore
he cannot even ignore it anymore because
it's impossible to ignore
like even when you think you're ignoring
things you're only ignoring
pretty much the responsibility for your
choices but you you wouldn't be able to make
but you you wouldn't be able to make
choices even in a state of half
awareness that most people live in
their choices this you're still aware of
them so that whole delusion and ignoring
and unawareness it's not this
mystical non-existence or some mystery
that you don't know
it's you actively ignoring part of the
picture ignoring your responsibility for
opening the gate
ignoring your responsibility for letting
people in or trying to chase them out
either way opening the door
but either way you cannot ignore it for
as long as you're alive
because that's what being alive is being
conscious being aware so when people say oh come
being aware so when people say oh come
back to the present moment you have no
choice about
it you are in the present moment whether
you want or not
or but what you should do is stop
ignoring responsibility for the present
moment stop ignoring that fundamentally it's
stop ignoring that fundamentally it's
your choice
that has all these various symptoms
later on arising and bothering you
choice of lust choice of ill will choice
of ignoring responsibility
delusion choice of oblivion
choice of carelessness and as we begin
begun this talk
none of these things would manifest
unless you acted out of them and unless
you keep acting out of them by
body speech and mind
available so yes protect the behavior of
your body
of your speech and your mind and the
buddha said the skillful monk practices
like this
he's gonna you know he will restrain his
behavior he'll restrain his speech then
he's gonna have still like thoughts of
cruelty course sensuality arise for him but he
course sensuality arise for him but he
sustains his practice
these thoughts will diminish then he's
going to have subtler thoughts
you know like subtler annoyances
thoughts of his clan
country reputation kind of
broader subtler things then that will
subside and then he's just going to have
and then he's just going to have
thoughts of purity of dhamma
like things as they are literally like
in scene just the scene in her just the
herd and thought just a thought
so no more corruption no more confusion
about the gateway
but again that doesn't happen magically
he clearly understood what not to be
done and then he kept a watchful eye
peripherally on things that are about to
be done
and then didn't do them if they were
unwholesome if they're wholesome kept an
eye on them and allowed them to be done
but not just physically but verbally and
mentally that's why often the buddha would you
that's why often the buddha would you
know give all those instructions about
the speech and careless speech and
malicious speech and even if it's not
coursely bad speech
pointless speech are you just chit
chatting for whatever reason
means you are now choosing to maintain
the kind of like because you cannot
engage in a careless chit chat
verbally without that implying a certain
obliviousness uh on the level of your mind a certain
uh on the level of your mind a certain
like careless pointless choice of a distraction
distraction
so and that's what you want to arrive
ultimately the clarity
of your thoughts in regard to present
and during pressure of any hindrance
whether it's sensuality ill will
restlessness doubt remorse
sluggishness doesn't matter
it's rooted in the mind but you will not
see that for as long as you physically
immediately act out of it
for as long as you verbally act out of
it
but if you don't you get to see that oh
look i'm cultivating such and such
thoughts when this hindrance is present
i am choosing
literally i am choosing when these
things are present
i make a choice
for these thoughts to start to move
so what if i just choose not to do that
not like i choose to get rid of this
because you can't so you endure it but i
choose to not entertain such and such
thoughts and then you sustain
the choice for which recognition of that
thing enduring there is still necessary
it's implicit
so you cannot not be mindful with such
practice that's the meditation that's that's
that's the meditation that's that's
amadi that's the humility
being able to sustain it to compose it
compose it the right way and sustain it
maintain it in the being paving it
the samadhi of patience patient injury
well yeah it's one of the factors
if you practice patience rightly you
will develop somebody
patience in regards to right things not
patience in regards to you know enduring
ants biting me
why but what's the reason for it
but yeah and during the pressure of the
certain choices that you know are
unwholesome and you don't do throughout the day from
and you don't do throughout the day from
the moment you wake up
the more you go to bed and we said that
before a useful practice would be at the
end of the day
not as a sort of mantra or something
just sit down and see
have there been instances during the day
where you actually acted out of things
that were that should have not been
acted out when you acted out of last
year will
and if you remember yes i did i said
such and such thing in the morning it
was careless
don't go through this like psychotherapy
motions or if i will ask
forgiveness and stuff i mean you do it
whatever but it's pointless
but what you want to do that it's not
pointless is recognized there and then
rediscern the gateway because of which
you've done such a thing in the morning
that's the way to deal with it oh
remember your responsibility remember
your responsibility so i'll never do
that again i don't know if i'm going to
do it again or not
but how do i do it whenever i do do it
by losing the side of the gate
why oh this gateway that now i'm losing
the sight off because i'm so obsessed
with this remorse and making
determination that i will never
make this mistake again and yet you're
doing it right there and then
ignoring the gateway and that's it